<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><REPORT><ELEMENT><SUBJECT><NAME></NAME><DOB></DOB><MR></MR><REFPH></REFPH><DIAG>Medically refractory partial epilepsy</DIAG><DOE></DOE><HIST></HIST></SUBJECT><TECHSUMMARY><TITLE>Technical Summary</TITLE><SECTION><TITLE>MEG and EEG recording</TITLE><TEXT>MEG data were collected in a seated position within a magnetically shielded room, using a 306-channel biomagnetometer unit. The channel array consisted of 204 planar gradiometers and 102 magnetometers distributed at each of 102 locations around the head.  The MEG data was acquired at a sampling rate of 2000 Hz.&#10;EEG was recorded simultaneously with the MEG, using a 64 contact cap electrode system EEG was recorded with a right mastoid reference, at the same sampling rate as the MEG.&#10;&#10;EEG data recorded along with the MEG was also visually reviewed by an experienced electroencephalographer to assess background activity and identify epileptiform abnormalities.</TEXT></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Tasks for evoked responses</TITLE><TASK name="SOMATO" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="AUDDEFNAME" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="WORDRECOGNITION" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="HANDMOTOR" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="CUSTOM" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="SPIKES" include="1"></TASK></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>MEG and EEG analysis</TITLE><TEXT>The MEG signals recorded were first subjected to automated artifact and noise filtering using the Signal Space Separation method available on the Elekta Neuromag MEG acquisition system. Additional filtering of EKG artifacts was then performed using Principal Component Analysis. The resulting data was visual screened to verify the quality of the recording. &#10;After artifact filtering, MEG segments recorded during functional tasks were subjected to event-locked averaging to extract evoked responses.&#10;All recorded MEG traces were visually screened by an epileptologiest to identify and mark epileptiform spikes or sharp waves for source localization.</TEXT></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Magnetic Source Imaging</TITLE><TASK name="HEADMODEL" include="1"></TASK><TASK name="DIPOLEMODEL" include="1"></TASK><TEXT>Additional analysis of the data using distributed source imaging methods was performed using the Brainstorm software package. Results based on distributed source estimation methodologies are presented in the Appendix, since the software tools and analytical methods used have yet to be standardized across MEG centers.</TEXT></SECTION></TECHSUMMARY><MEGRESULTS><TITLE>MEG Results</TITLE><TEXT></TEXT><SECTION><TITLE>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</TITLE><TASK name="SOMATO" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="AUDDEFNAME" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="WORDRECOGNITION" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="HANDMOTOR" include="0"></TASK><TASK name="CUSTOM" include="0"></TASK></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Epileptiform activity</TITLE><TASK include="1" name="SPIKES"></TASK></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Ictal recording</TITLE></SECTION></MEGRESULTS><EEGRESULTS><TITLE>EEG results</TITLE><SECTION><TITLE></TITLE><TEXT>The simultaneously recorded 64 channel EEG recording was reviewed visually.&#10;Background:&#10;Epileptiform activity:&#10;Sleep:&#10;EKG:&#10;No clinical or electrographic seizures were noted on EEG during the course of this recording.</TEXT></SECTION></EEGRESULTS><SUMMARY><TITLE>Summary and Clinical correlation</TITLE><SECTION><TITLE>Summary</TITLE><TEXT>This is an abnormal MEG-EEG study due to the following abnormalities:&#10;Source of motor and somatosensory evoked responses localize to areas corresponding to anatomical sensory and motor areas in the peri-rolandic cortices on both sides. As expected, motor responses localized anterior to the somatosensory regions. No clinical or electrographic seizures were captured to permit ictal source imaging.&#10;Language-task evoked responses were strongly lateralized to the left hemisphere.</TEXT></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Clinical Correlation</TITLE><TEXT></TEXT></SECTION></SUMMARY><SIGN><TITLE></TITLE><SECTION><TITLE>Reported by</TITLE><TASK name="SIGNNAME" include="1"></TASK></SECTION></SIGN><APPENDIX><TITLE>Appendix</TITLE><SECTION><TITLE>Disclaimer</TITLE><TEXT>This section summarizes the results of additional analyses of the MEG data, primarily using distributed source imaging methods. Though these source estimation methods have been validated in many peer-reviewed publications, this section is provided for use at the clinician's descretion since the source imaging software is not FDA approved and the analytical procedures performed on the source estimates have yet to be standardized across clinical MEG centers.</TEXT></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Distributed source modeling methods</TITLE><TASK include="1" name="DISTRIBMODEL"></TASK></SECTION><SECTION><TITLE>Distributed source modeling results</TITLE><TASK include="1" name="DISTRIBMODEL"></TASK></SECTION></APPENDIX></ELEMENT><PROTOCOL><HEADMODEL><TITLE>Head modeling</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Magnetic Source Imaging</SECTION><TEXT>The patient's 3-D Volumetric MR data, acquired separately, was used to define a sperical single-shell head model using the Neuromag analysis software.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION></SECTION><IMAGES></IMAGES></RESULTS></HEADMODEL><DIPOLEMODEL><TITLE>Dipole modeling</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Magnetic Source Imaging</SECTION><TEXT> Dipolar modeling of epileptic spike events that were identified in the MEG sensor data and the averaged evoked responses during median nerve stimulation and hand motor activity was performed using the xfit routines in the Neuromag analysis package. Dipole fitting was performed for all time-points within a small temporal window (20-100 ms) centered around the spike, and the best fitting dipole was identified. A goodness-of-fit criterion of >80% was used in this analysis to determine whether to retain or reject a spike dipole model.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION></SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES></IMAGES></RESULTS></DIPOLEMODEL><DISTRIBMODEL><TITLE></TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Distributed source modeling methods</SECTION><TEXT>The methodologies used in the data analyses detailed below merges the anatomical information from the patient's T1-weighted MRI data with MEG source analysis. The scalp and grey matter surfaces were extracted from the MRI volume data using automated tissue segmentation and surface tessellation techniques. The brain surface was subsequently sampled with elementary dipole sources which position and orientation were constrained to the cortical surface. This spatial sampling of the cortex is typically achieved using about 15,000 elementary current sources, separated by about 3 mm. These elementary sources may be viewed as image voxels whose intensity is estimated at every time sample of the MEG recording.&#10;&#10;It is generally acknowledged that this approach to MEG souce modeling is capable of accounting for the origins of multifocal and rapidly-evolving brain activity with a fair spatial resolution (typically in the centimeter range).</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Distributed source modeling results</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES></IMAGES></RESULTS></DISTRIBMODEL><SPIKES><TITLE>Spontaneous epileptiform activity</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT>Additional 15 minutes of spontaneous data was acquired over 3 sessions lasting 5 minutes each to search for interictal or ictal epileptiform abnormalities. MEG samples acquired during the functional mapping tasks were also reviewed for epileptiform abnomalities.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Epileptiform activity</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES><LABEL src="" title="Figure">Sensor level distribution of typical spike: The figure above displays a representative epileptic spike from this patient on a subset of 102 magnetometers. The left side of the panel shows the recorded MEG tracings from the magnetometers. On the right, the MEG sensors are represented as a flattened array (patient's nose pointing upwards, and left side of head on the viewer's left). About 150ms are displayed on each side of the green vertical marker for each sensor.</LABEL><LABEL src="" title="Figure">Dipolar sources of interictal spikes: Figure 2, above, shows single-dipole models for the epileptiform spikes identified in the MEG recordings. Sources are shown displayed on "glass-brain" sagittal, axial, and coronal views (so all dipoles appear in the plane of the brain displayed), as well as 3-D views from the right, left and bottom. Dipole models were computed over a +/- 50ms window cntered on the earliest spike peak in the MEG sensor traces. The colors o fthe dipoles encode time (blue being earliest and red the last to appear). Dipole orientation is indicated by the tails of the point sources. Only dipoles with a goodness of fit > 80% are shown here. The dipolar sources are maximally concentrated</LABEL></IMAGES></RESULTS></SPIKES><SOMATO><TITLE>Primary somatosensory mapping</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT>Controlled electrical stimulation (5ms duration, amplitude individually determined to evoke thumb twitching, 100 repetitions for each hand) were delivered to the patient during MEG recording.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES><LABEL src="" title="Figure">Left and right median nerve stimulation: The figure above shows the dipolar sources of the averaged responses to median nerve stimulation.</LABEL></IMAGES></RESULTS></SOMATO><AUDDEFNAME><TITLE>Language mapping</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT>MEG recording was performed during an auditory definition naming language task. The subject was presented a definition of an object, or place and was required to verbally respond aloud with a common noun or proper noun. A control task was also performed where a series of between 1 to 4 tones were presented admixed with the noise sounds that were spectrally matched to speech sounds. On each trial, the subject's task was to state aloud the number of tones presented. Each stimulus type was presented 90 times over 6 blocks of trials to estimate the average stimulus-locked MEG responses.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES></IMAGES></RESULTS></AUDDEFNAME><WORDRECOGNITION><TITLE>Language mapping</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT>MEG recording was performed during a language task. The subject was randomly presented words, irregular words, pseudo-words, and strings of visual symbols (Japanese Kanji). The subject's task was to say the word aloud, or verbally indicate the non-word status of the stimulus presented on each trial. Each stimulus type was presented 90 times over 6 blocks of trials to estimate the average stimulus-locked MEG responses.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES><LABEL src="" title="Figure">Language task evoked responses: The figure above shows the dipolar sources of responses evoked by a word identification task for the temporal window from 350 to 450ms after stimulus presentation.</LABEL></IMAGES></RESULTS></WORDRECOGNITION><HANDMOTOR><TITLE>Hand motor mapping</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT>The subject performed visually-cued tapping of the index fingers or cleanching/unclenching of the hand (50 repetitions, each side). The visual cue comprised of a Gaussian \"blob\" that appears at variable intervals and a visual fixation mark presented on a LCD screen. The cue duration was 50ms. The subject is asked to initiate motor activiity when each cue is presented. The precise time of movement is recorded by a finger pad sensor. The ongoing MEG activity was averaged for each movement type using the movement time markers.</TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES><LABEL src="" title="Figure">Motor evoked responses: The image above summarizes dipolar sources of evoked neuromagnetic activity during uilateral visually-cued hand motor activity.</LABEL></IMAGES></RESULTS></HANDMOTOR><CUSTOM><TITLE>Insert title here</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION>Tasks for evoked responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Stimulus-evoked functional responses</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES></IMAGES></RESULTS></CUSTOM><SIGNNAME><TITLE>Reported by</TITLE><TECHNICAL><SECTION></SECTION><TEXT></TEXT></TECHNICAL><RESULTS><SECTION>Reported by</SECTION><TEXT></TEXT><IMAGES><LABEL src="sylvain.jpg" title="">Sylvain Baillet, Ph.D. (MEG/Neuroscience)</LABEL><LABEL src="manoj.jpg" title="">Manoj Raghavan, M.D., Ph.D. (Epilepsy/EEG/MEG)</LABEL></IMAGES></RESULTS></SIGNNAME></PROTOCOL></REPORT>